<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Movies on Michael's Blog</title><link>https://blog.michael.gr/tags/movies/</link><description>Recent content in Movies on Michael's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Michael Belivanakis (a.k.a. Mike Nakis)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 09:39:51 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.michael.gr/tags/movies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Movie: Dawn of the Planet of the Apes</title><link>https://blog.michael.gr/post/2014-12-movie-dawn-of-planet-of-apes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2014 23:32:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.michael.gr/post/2014-12-movie-dawn-of-planet-of-apes/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This post does not contain any spoilers, unless you would consider as a spoiler my opinion on how the quality if the movie varies as the movie progresses. (Or the image below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center"&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.michael.gr/post/2014-12-movie-dawn-of-planet-of-apes/media/dawn-planet-apes-trailer.jpg"
width="900"
height="540"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="166"
data-flex-basis="400px"
&gt;
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;Picture source: &lt;a class="external"
href="https://www.cgmeetup.net/home/dawn-of-the-planet-of-the-apes-official-international-trailer-2/" target="_blank"
&gt;cgmeetup.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I watched &lt;em&gt;The Dawn of the Planet of the Apes&lt;/em&gt; yesterday, and what can I say, wow, it blew my mind. I started watching it having very low expectations, and I was very pleasantly surprised for about one hour and fifty minutes of its total two hour and ten minute duration, which includes the end titles. Then, starting with the &amp;quot;I am saving the human race&amp;quot; incident, it transformed into the crap that I had expected from the beginning, perhaps even worse, but that does not annul the fact that the first one hour and fifty minutes were one of the most pleasant movie watching experiences I have had in quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The movie has it all: an epic adventure, adequately developed characters, complex interpersonal dynamics among the main characters, awesome animations thanks to extensive use of motion capture technology, extremely well done &amp;amp; never-seen-before expressiveness in the faces of the animated characters due to the use of facial expression tracking technology, the right amount of suspense, the right amount of sentiment, and the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center"&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.michael.gr/post/2014-12-movie-dawn-of-planet-of-apes/media/dawn-planet-apes-split-two.jpg"
width="648"
height="538"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="120"
data-flex-basis="289px"
&gt;
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;Picture source:&lt;a class="external"
href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/behind-screen/dawn-planet-apes-director-creating-717858" target="_blank"
&gt;hollywoodreporter.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why am I writing this post? Well, I wanted to share one little thing which really caught my attention when I realized it was going on (well into the movie) and which really spoke to my inner geek. It was the way that the apes spoke. It caught my attention because it had to do with scientific accuracy: you rarely see Hollywood bothering to do one of the little things right, so this was quite unexpected and quite welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the movie, when you hear apes talk, you will notice that they say one, maybe two words, then they pause, then they say another one or two words, pause again, and so on. In the beginning you might think that the director is trying to show that the apes are a bit too dumb to properly articulate speech, but as the movie progresses you realize that these apes are clearly capable of quite complex mental tasks, so it does not seem to add up. Inevitably, the realization dawns upon you: Apes in this movie speak like that because that's precisely how apes would actually speak regardless of how dumb or smart they were. &lt;em&gt;It is the movie trying to be realistic.&lt;/em&gt; (And being awesomely successful at it, at least with respect to this little detail.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center"&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.michael.gr/post/2014-12-movie-dawn-of-planet-of-apes/media/dawn-planet-apes-7.jpg"
width="960"
height="516"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="186"
data-flex-basis="446px"
&gt;
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center"&gt;Picture source: &lt;a class="external"
href="https://www.graffitiwithpunctuation.net/2014/07/03/review-dawn-planet-apes-matt-reeves-2014/" target="_blank"
&gt;graffitiwithpunctuation.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, the fact of the matter is not only that real apes today, in the labs, do in fact speak their limited vocabularies exactly like that, but most importantly, that even if they were to become much smarter, (as the apes in The Planet of the Apes saga supposedly are,) they would &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; speak exactly like that. They are incapable of speaking the way we do, and that's due to a simple biological reason which has nothing to do with intellect: &lt;em&gt;apes cannot control their breath as we do&lt;/em&gt;. It is very difficult to be eloquent when half the words come out while exhaling, while the other half come out while inhaling. This is all very well documented fact, ask any primatologist about it, and I just happen to know it due to my side-interest in evolutionary biology and biological anthropology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do the smart apes in The Dawn Of The Planet Of The Apes do? They only speak while exhaling. This only gives them enough time to utter a word or two; then they pause while inhaling; and then they say another couple of words; and so on. Of course, this situation compels them to be rather laconic in anything they say, and to resort to speaking in sign language among themselves. Fantastically well rendered.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The exploding hatch in the movie Sunshine (2007)</title><link>https://blog.michael.gr/post/2007-09-23-exploding-hatch-in-sunshine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2007 01:16:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.michael.gr/post/2007-09-23-exploding-hatch-in-sunshine/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.michael.gr/post/2007-09-23-exploding-hatch-in-sunshine/media/sunshine-1.jpg"
width="4425"
height="1863"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="237"
data-flex-basis="570px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie &amp;quot;Sunshine&amp;quot; by Danny Boyle (&lt;a class="external"
href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0448134/" target="_blank"
&gt;IMDB&lt;/a&gt;) there is a scene which is impossible to comprehend unless you have some knowledge of physics. The protagonist Robert Capa (Cillian Murphy) finds himself trapped in an airlock from which he must escape at any cost. The airlock contains a space suit, and has one outer hatch towards space, and one inner hatch towards the interior of the spaceship, which is locked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capa first uses a blowtorch to bore a tiny hole on the inner hatch; then, he wears the spacesuit, fastens himself securely so that he won't be blown away, and presses the button which opens the outer hatch. The airlock decompresses violently to the outer void, and for a split second nothing else seems to happen, but immediately afterwards the inner hatch gets mysteriously blown away too, and the atmosphere of the ship escapes, (together with many objects from its interior,) through the airlock, to space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few moments the flow of debris abates, and Capa is able to enter the ship. (Do not try this at home.) The movie does not spend any time explaining the cause of the explosion of the inner hatch; for those who got it, fine; for the rest, it is a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.michael.gr/post/2007-09-23-exploding-hatch-in-sunshine/media/sunshine-2.jpg"
width="3008"
height="2002"
loading="lazy"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="150"
data-flex-basis="360px"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What blew up the inner hatch was the tiny hole that Capa bore on it before decompressing the airlock. It works exactly the same way a pin prick causes a balloon to explode. You can read all about it in &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balloon_popping" target="_blank"
&gt;Wikipedia: Balloon popping&lt;/a&gt; but I think I can do a better job at explaining it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every point on the balloon's surface experiences an outward force due to the pressure differential between the inside and the outside of the balloon, but it is kept in place due to its bonds with the material surrounding it. Thus, under normal conditions, the forces balance out, and the balloon is in equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if a tiny hole is made on the balloon's surface, the bonds are disturbed: the points around the hole do not have enough bonds with surrounding material anymore to keep them in place. As a result, they start pulling away, making the hole slightly bigger; the bigger hole allows more air to escape, thus, increasing the imbalance, and causing the points around the hole to pull away even more. This is a &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positive_feedback" target="_blank"
&gt;reinforcing feedback loop&lt;/a&gt;, which results in catastrophic escalation of the rate at which the hole expands; in other words, the balloon explodes.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>