<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>fringe-theories on Michael&#39;s Blog</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/tags/fringe-theories/</link>
        <description>Recent content in fringe-theories on Michael&#39;s Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Michael Belivanakis (a.k.a. Mike Nakis)</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 18:59:55 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/fringe-theories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>On the Tired Light Hypothesis</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/post/2025-07-tired-light-hypothesis/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 12:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/post/2025-07-tired-light-hypothesis/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/post/2025-07-tired-light-hypothesis/images/tired-light.svg&#34;
	
	
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-static-universe&#34;&gt;The Static Universe
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first model of cosmology that I was exposed to, as a small child, was that of the static universe, because that&amp;rsquo;s all my father knew. According to that model, the universe is infinite in all directions, it is eternal, and it is not going anywhere. Of course I accepted it, because that is what kids do: accept everything presented to them as fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-expanding-universe&#34;&gt;The Expanding Universe
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, during elementary school, I heard of the Big Bang and the expansion of the universe; this new model of cosmology made me feel a bit uncomfortable, but again I accepted it, because a) that&amp;rsquo;s what the scientists said, and b) I could go to my father and tell him that he is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-cosmological-red-shift&#34;&gt;The Cosmological Red-Shift
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later, during my junior high-school years, I heard of the red-shift of galaxies, as simply the Doppler effect applied to light, and it sounded reasonable, but then I heard of &lt;em&gt;cosmological&lt;/em&gt; red-shift, as the stretching of photon wavelengths due to expansion of space itself. That sounded very exotic to me. I was again willing to accept it, because scientists had said so, but I was now starting to feel uncomfortable, because I am not into pretending to understand things that I do not truly understand. (Furthermore, my father had no concept of such things, so I could not even start a discussion with him with the goal of showing him that he is wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-accelerating-expansion&#34;&gt;The Accelerating Expansion
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then I started hearing of truly bizarre observations, such as that galaxies in all directions around us are red-shifted, meaning that they are all moving away from us. When I want to comically express my bewilderment at this, I raise my arms, smell my armpits, and say &amp;ldquo;why, what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with us?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned that according to red-shift observations, the farther away a galaxy is, the faster it is moving away from us, and that not only the galaxies are moving away from each other, but the rate at which they are moving is increasing, meaning that galaxies are accelerating away from each other. Again I accepted all that because scientists had said so, but by that time it was already clear to me that I was accepting these things only because I had no other option. A little something in me was finding all this uncomfortable to the point of being disturbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dark-matter-and-dark-energy&#34;&gt;Dark Matter and Dark Energy
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The apex of my discomfort came during my last year of senior high-school, when I started hearing of dark matter and dark energy; popular media portrayed them as discoveries, but a closer examination of what the scientists were actually saying revealed that they were nothing but fictitious notions that scientists had dreamt up in order to explain the observations, otherwise the numbers did not add up. In other words, the scientists had given names to their ignorance. And it was not just some small discrepancies that these novelties were called to correct for; dark matter and dark energy were supposed to account for about 95% of the universe. On the surface I was okay with this, because again, scientists had said so, but that little something in me had now started finding all this quite preposterous and becoming genuinely disturbed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop for a moment and think how arrogant this is on our behalf: we are saying &amp;ldquo;here are our observations of the universe,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;here are our theories to explain those observations,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;by the way, our theories only explain 5% of the observations, the remaining 95% is inexplicable.&amp;rdquo; And instead of admitting that our theories are worthless, we take it for granted that they are correct, and we assume that there must be some other, as of yet completely unknown, and completely unobserved mechanisms at play, which account for the missing 95%, so that our theories end up being correct. To top it all off, we come up with a couple of cool names for those mechanisms, to make the public think that we actually have a clue as to what we are talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And wait, that&amp;rsquo;s not all; we are even saying that other than exerting gravitational pull, dark matter does not seem to interact with regular matter, not even with itself, so it is virtually unobservable. This inevitably brings to mind the skeptic argument about the invisible, untouchable, and odorless realm of the supernatural as being virtually indistinguishable from the non-existent. To put it in more scientific terms, &lt;em&gt;is this shit even falsifiable?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-idea&#34;&gt;My Idea
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;All this was so disturbing to me, that in order to retain my sanity I was forced to invest some thinking into it, despite the hopelessness of the endeavor, given that I have no formal background in physics, let alone astrophysics; my field is, and has always been, software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My thinking was, necessarily, simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no doubt that relative movement of galaxies in space is at least partially responsible for the observed red-shift, just as it is responsible for the few cases of observed blue-shift. For example the Andromeda galaxy is blue-shifted, because it is on a collision course with the Milky Way. However, this does not mean that relative movement is necessarily responsible for all of the observed red-shift. Can we find some additional means of explaining red-shift so that we might account for those manifestations of it that are truly bizarre?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to think what it means to say that the fabric of space is expanding. How do we know that it is expanding? Could it be that the only way that we know that it is expanding is due to the observed red-shift? If so, then what is the difference, really, between saying that the fabric of space is expanding, and saying that the frequency of light that is dropping? How do we know that it is one and not the other?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, I arrived at my hypothesis: If light happens to have an as of yet unknown property which causes its frequency to ever so slightly decrease as it travels through the vast expanses of intergalactic space, then clearly, the result would appear as red-shift. That would beautifully explain at least two observations that are currently receiving disturbing explanations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Light reaching us from any galaxy has to travel a long distance, therefore all galaxies should appear red-shifted, as they indeed do, even though they might be more or less stationary with respect to us. This is a much simpler explanation than to say that all galaxies are running away from us as if we have smelly armpits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Light reaching us from distant galaxies has to travel a longer distance than from nearby galaxies, therefore more distant galaxies should appear more red-shifted, as they indeed do. This is a much simpler explanation than to say that galaxies are not only moving away from us, but actually accelerating away from us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew that my idea had at least a tiny bit of merit due to Occam&amp;rsquo;s razor: sure, I was postulating the existence of some hypothetical property of light that causes its frequency to decrease as it travels through space, but:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a terribly implausible thing to suppose, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems far less implausible than proposing an expanding universe, an expanding fabric of space, plus dark matter and dark energy to make the numbers add up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, Occam&amp;rsquo;s razor says that if two hypotheses have equal explaining power, the simpler one wins. What remained to be seen was whether my hypothesis did actually have equal explaining power as the established scientific theories. I suspected it did not, due to reasons beyond my level of comprehension of the universe, but I had no one to ask, and therefore no way of knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had this idea in my late teens, and not knowing what to do with it, I stored it in the back of my mind and went on with my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;asking-around&#34;&gt;Asking around
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I was at California State University, San Bernardino I had a cool professor who came to the classroom one day with an inflatable balloon that had galaxies printed on it. By inflating the balloon, she showed how the expansion of the fabric of space can explain the observation that all galaxies are seemingly moving away from us, as well as from each other; I could accept this, but it only took care of the smelly armpits problem; the highly exotic notion of an expanding fabric of space was still there, the troublesome acceleration of the expansion was also still there, and the preposterous notions of dark matter and dark energy were still there. So, I felt that my hypothesis had lost virtually none of its explanatory merit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the mid 2000s, in the golden era of internet blogs, and before facebook destroyed everything, I happened to have access to an audience of a few thousand people with higher than average education. A sizable portion of them were necessarily scientists, so a few of them were bound to be astrophysicists. This prompted me to describe my idea on my blog and ask if anyone had heard of anything similar to it. Sure enough, a couple of folks stepped up to inform me that my idea had already been considered by scientists, and that although not completely devoid of scientific merit, it was regarded as false, and it had pretty much been proven wrong by experimental observations. It even had a name: The &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tired Light Hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was an elating moment for me; there I was, a lay-person with respect to astrophysics, who had, at a relatively young age, independently arrived at a hypothesis that had also been considered by actual astrophysicists. I figured that was a substantial accomplishment, even if the hypothesis did not turn out to be correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course it would have been even more elating if they had said &amp;ldquo;hey, wow, guess what, we never thought of this, and you know what? you might actually be right!&amp;rdquo; but let us be serious, what are the chances of that happening?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fringe-theories&#34;&gt;Fringe Theories
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am weary of the phenomenon of fringe theories, where certain ideas seem to exert an irresistible appeal to non-scientists, causing misinformation to spread. I also happen to be somewhat partial to another fringe theory, which is the Aquatic Ape Hypothesis, and while delving into it back in the early &amp;rsquo;90s I witnessed the controversy that it stirred: large numbers of non-biologists loving it, virtually every biologist wishing that it would just die so that people would stop pestering them with it. When David Attenborough endorsed the hypothesis, the scientific community very nearly cancelled him. Even I, despite the fact that I liked the hypothesis, thought that it had been kind of risky on his behalf to endorse it. So, I am fully aware of the fact that these are fringe theories, and I am not insisting on anything, I am just amused at how much explanatory power they have. I regard them as very interesting curiosities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion I cannot help but mention that it gives me a warm, fuzzy feeling to keep note, somewhere in the back of my mind, of the fact that &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continental_drift&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continental Drift&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was also, for a long time, regarded by the scientific community as nothing but a fringe theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Static_universe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Wikipedia: Static Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
See &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Bang&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Wikipedia: Big Bang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
See &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expansion_of_the_universe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Wikipedia: Expansion of the universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
See &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tired_light&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Wikipedia: Tired Light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
See &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fringe_theory&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Wikipedia: Fringe Theory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover image: &amp;ldquo;Tired Light&amp;rdquo; vector graphic by michael.gr created with InkScape using parts of &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://thenounproject.com/icon/sinusoid-37912/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;&amp;ldquo;Sinusoid&amp;rdquo; by Yohann Berger from the Noun Project&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://thenounproject.com/icon/stars-602908/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;&amp;ldquo;Stars&amp;rdquo; by Ken Murray from the Noun Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>On the evolutionary origin of reasoning</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/post/2024-10-reasoning/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 11:24:24 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/post/2024-10-reasoning/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/post/2024-10-reasoning/images/caveman-thinking-1.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;1080&#34;
	height=&#34;1080&#34;
	srcset=&#34;//localhost:1313/post/2024-10-reasoning/images/caveman-thinking-1_hu_a680d3065694d80.jpg 480w, //localhost:1313/post/2024-10-reasoning/images/caveman-thinking-1_hu_b7767b2efb905834.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;100&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;240px&#34;
	
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biological anthropologists generally agree that humans evolved reasoning to facilitate hunting together as a group; however, there are many other species that hunt in packs, and yet reasoning is unique to humans. Therefore, in order to explain reasoning, it is not enough to consider how it was beneficial to us; we also need to consider what enabled reasoning to emerge specifically in humans as opposed to any other species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a hypothesis which attempts to explain how this happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Useful pre-reading: &lt;a 
   href=&#34;//localhost:1313/post/2022-11-about-these-papers/&#34;
   &gt;About these papers&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;exaptation-of-neural-circuitry-for-arboreal-navigation&#34;&gt;Exaptation of Neural Circuitry for Arboreal Navigation
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;A hypothesis for the emergence of reasoning in early humans&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When our &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simian&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;simian&lt;/a&gt; ancestors first stepped down from the canopy of the forest to the ground of the savanna, they were still pretty well adapted to arboreal life, so they still had with them all the machinery necessary for &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arboreal_locomotion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;arboreal locomotion&lt;/a&gt; by means of &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brachiation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;brachiation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of that machinery was evident in their anatomy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stereopsis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Stereoscopic vision&lt;/a&gt; for determining distances to branches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thumb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Opposable thumbs&lt;/a&gt; for grabbing and holding on to branches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper_limb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Strong upper limbs&lt;/a&gt; for suspending the entire body weight from a branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The machinery also included a very important element in the brain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neural_circuit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Neural circuits&lt;/a&gt; dedicated to the planning and execution of arboreal navigation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as brachiation is a formidable feat of the simian anatomy, so is arboreal navigation a formidable feat of the simian brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting from branch A to branch Z in the forest canopy involves examination of multiple alternative routes, each consisting of several successive leaps from branch to branch, where at each branch multiple choices are open, but some choices lead to dead-ends. Leaps often have to be evaluated in advance (planning) not only in order to determine the feasibility of the route as a whole, but also to find the most optimal route. The process involves some techniques which we have only started to grasp in the era of information processing, through the study of &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pathfinding&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;pathfinding&lt;/a&gt; algorithms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back-tracking: when the next leap in the path is deemed as not feasible, an alternative route can be sought from an earlier branch in the same path instead of starting from the beginning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information reuse: when it has been determined that from a certain branch X there is a path to reach branch Y, this information can be reused when an alternative way is found for arriving at branch X.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reverse pathfinding: to plan a path from branch A to branch Z one can start from A, consider leaps to branches near A, and so on; however, if most of those seem to lead to dead ends, one may alternatively plan a path by doing the reverse: starting from Z, considering feasible leaps to Z from branches near Z, and so on, until a branch is found which is known to be reachable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brachiation is an activity that simians carry out effortlessly, at incredibly high speeds, and flawlessly, because a single mistake can easily result in a
broken bone, which equates to certain death in the wild. Furthermore, (and I do not know this for sure, but I think it is a pretty safe guess,) simian
babies do not have to learn how to brachiate, they are pretty much born with the ability. Therefore, the simian brain must have built-in neural circuits specifically dedicated to the task of arboreal navigation and the planning thereof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once our simian ancestors settled on the ground of the savanna, the neural circuits for arboreal navigation fell into disuse, essentially becoming &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vestigiality&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;vestigial&lt;/a&gt;. At the same time, new challenges and opportunities arose: food on the savanna was scarce, so humans had to hunt. The hunt was generally big, and humans did not have claws and teeth, so they had to coordinate in order to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hypothesis is that via mechanisms that I cannot claim to know, (since I am not a bioanthropologist, nor a neurobiologist,) the neural circuitry for arboreal navigation was repurposed in the human brain for the task of reasoning. Repurposing of traits is known by evolutionary biology to be common, not only in anatomy but also in behavior; it is called &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exaptation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;exaptation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anatomical machinery that enabled simians to brachiate is still present in us today, so it is not a stretch to imagine that the neural machinery is also present. Human babies have a lot to learn until they can function autonomously in the world, but reasoning comes rather naturally to them, and education seems to build upon a preexisting foundation which innately supports reasoning. Therefore, reasoning seems to also be largely based on dedicated neural circuitry in the human brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental workflows of reasoning and arboreal navigation bear a striking resemblance to each other: from a certain set of premises, a number of potential inferences can be examined; some of those can be ignored due to being irrelevant to the desired conclusion; they correspond to leaps in directions away from the desired destination. Other potential inferences can be disregarded due to being false; these correspond to leaps that are impossible to make. Each of the remaining inferences represents a new set of premises, from which further potential inferences can be examined, thus bringing us closer and closer to the desired conclusion. Some chains of inferences lead to dead-ends, at which point we go back one or more steps to examine a different path; these correspond to back-tracking in path-finding. In all these cases, the neural circuitry we use for reasoning may be that very same neural circuitry that we used to use for arboreal navigation but fell into disuse when we came down from the trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The necessity to coordinate for hunting may have acted as a catalyst for the repurposing of neural circuitry from the task of arboreal navigation to the task of reasoning. The Gorilla is another great ape that descended from the trees to the ground, but they have remained vegetarian, so their food was free for the grabbing in the trees, and continued to be free for the grabbing on the ground. Therefore, Gorillas had no need to form packs and go hunting for food, and thus no evolutionary pressure to do any repurposing of neural circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More light might be shed on this hypothesis from research on the anatomical connectivity between the &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cerebellum&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;cerebellum&lt;/a&gt;, which is associated with motor control, and the &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frontal_lobe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;frontal lobe&lt;/a&gt;, which is associated with problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover image: &amp;ldquo;Thinking Caveman&amp;rdquo;, AI-generated at &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://canva.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;canva.com&lt;/a&gt; from a prompt by michael.gr&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
