<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Essays on Michael&#39;s Blog</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/tags/essays/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Essays on Michael&#39;s Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Michael Belivanakis (a.k.a. Mike Nakis)</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 19:53:27 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/essays/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>On Moore&#39;s Law</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/p/on-moores-law/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 07:25:13 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/p/on-moores-law/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/on-moores-law/images/moores-law.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;1920&#34;
	height=&#34;1200&#34;
	srcset=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/on-moores-law/images/moores-law_hu_c159cd8910a785dc.jpg 480w, //localhost:1313/p/on-moores-law/images/moores-law_hu_2a6ac2f363812ab6.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;160&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;384px&#34;
	
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not a law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It never was a law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An observation is all that it ever was, or a prediction, but not a law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And surprise, it does not hold true anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prophecy was false, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am appalled by the entire industry&amp;rsquo;s willingness to accept it being called a law, when it was clearly failing to meet the criteria for a law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember, when I heard the term for the first time, as a child, I felt there was something wrong about it; there was an objection inside of me wanting to get out, but I knew that no one around me cared to debate this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I remained silent, and I accepted the term, but only provisionally, under the excuse of poetic license, as a statement patently employing absurdity in order to impress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now the time has come that it does not impress anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover photo by &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@maxence_pira?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Maxence Pira&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/a-close-up-of-a-pattern-of-small-squares-7hR3FrFs4Q0?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The &#39;gay gene&#39; paradox</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/p/the-gay-gene-paradox/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 12:04:22 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/p/the-gay-gene-paradox/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/the-gay-gene-paradox/images/digitale-de-2GEr4fLZt8A-unsplash%281%29.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;2400&#34;
	height=&#34;1697&#34;
	srcset=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/the-gay-gene-paradox/images/digitale-de-2GEr4fLZt8A-unsplash%281%29_hu_b5a32545bb3b95d7.jpg 480w, //localhost:1313/p/the-gay-gene-paradox/images/digitale-de-2GEr4fLZt8A-unsplash%281%29_hu_4fee19744095e62d.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;141&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;339px&#34;
	
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What causes homosexuality? The predominant understanding is that the causes are genetic, but this seems to be in conflict with the notion of natural selection: an individual who does not reproduce is a dead-end for the genes that they carry; therefore, the &amp;lsquo;gay gene&amp;rsquo; should have gone extinct. A number of hypotheses have been proposed, attempting to resolve this paradox, but they are not very convincing. In this post I present a couple of my own hypotheses, which I believe do a better job at resolving the paradox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Useful pre-reading: &lt;a 
   href=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/about-these-papers/&#34;
   &gt;About these papers&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One prominent scientist who has publicly addressed the paradox of the &amp;lsquo;gay gene&amp;rsquo; is professor Richard Dawkins. In his YouTube Channel &amp;ldquo;The Poetry of Reality&amp;rdquo; he attempts to give some possible answers to the question, in a video titled &amp;ldquo;How is the &amp;lsquo;Gay Gene&amp;rsquo; alive?&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZPxztLWmbJM&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Y&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;environmental activation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis suggests that the gay gene&amp;rsquo;s primary function might be something unrelated to homosexuality, and it may manifest as homosexuality only if certain environmental factors are present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;gay uncle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis suggests that genes for homosexuality are passed on through relatives. A homosexual individual does not have offspring of their own to look after, so they look after other members of the extended family. This way, each member of the family has more caregivers, thus increasing the member&amp;rsquo;s chances of survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sneaky fucker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis suggests that homosexuals propagate the gene by using their perceived non-threatening nature to gain the trust of dominant males, thus being very successful at covertly mating with females.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not deny that these hypotheses have some explanatory merit, but I find them rather weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;environmental activation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis is weak because homosexuality has been studied so much, that if there were any such environmental factors, we would have known them by now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;gay uncle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis is weak because having additional caregivers within a family is a rather small benefit which does not offset the immediate and severe disadvantage of having individuals within the family who do not propagate their genes. If the gay uncle hypothesis worked, then every family should be having only one child at a time, so as to maximize the number of caregivers per child, but this directly contradicts known fact: the archetypal family always had as many children as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sneaky fucker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis is weak because it invokes some alleged non-threatening nature of homosexuals, which is entirely arbitrary, it assumes some complex social interactions which are actually rather rare among humans and have no equivalents in the (rest of the) animal kingdom, and it completely disregards the question of homosexuality among women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, instead of the above, I would like to propose another hypothesis which is very simple, accounts for lesbianism, and is also in line with what is observed in the (rest of the) animal kingdom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;bisexual propagator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;gay gene&amp;rsquo; puts individuals in a spectrum between homosexuality and bisexuality. Each individual who becomes strictly homosexual represents a dead-end for the gene, but each individual who becomes bisexual ensures the propagation of the gene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the sneaky fucker hypothesis is also based on the assumption that the &amp;lsquo;gay gene&amp;rsquo; proliferates by means of bisexuals; however, the rest of the mechanism proposed by that hypothesis is unwarranted: bisexuality is sufficient by itself to explain the proliferation of the &amp;lsquo;gay gene&amp;rsquo; without the need to invoke false stereotypes, without any complex social interactions, and without requiring any sneakiness in the fuckery. Also note that the sneaky fucker hypothesis is inapplicable to lesbianism, whereas the bisexual propagator hypothesis explains that too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hypotheses mentioned by professor Richard Dawkins could at best amplify the proliferation of the &amp;lsquo;gay gene&amp;rsquo; rather than fully explain it, but if we are looking for amplifying hypotheses there is another one that I would like to propose, which again, I believe, has a far greater explanatory power than either &amp;lsquo;gay uncle&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;sneaky fucker&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;reluctant propagator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The propagation of the &amp;lsquo;gay gene&amp;rsquo; is in part due to homosexuals being under very strong societal pressure to engage in heterosexual behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the greatest part of human history, and in the vast majority of cultures around the planet, the heterosexual majority has been treating the homosexual minority with extreme enmity. Sure, there have been some cultures in which homosexuality was accepted, but they are very few and far apart. Throughout human existence, homosexuality has, as a rule rather than an exception, been associated with severe social stigma. As a matter of fact, in most cultures, homosexuality has historically carried the death penalty, and in some places it still does. Any capable individual who did not seek to mate with the opposite sex and procreate could be suspected of being a homosexual, and would therefore suffer that stigma, and possibly even risk that fate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, due to societal pressure, homosexuals have historically had a very strong incentive to engage in heterosexual behavior, despite it being against their innate desires. (The desire to survive trumps all other desires. Even the desire to be socially accepted can trump many other desires.) The consequence of this is that people who would have otherwise lived a strictly homosexual lifestyle have ended up living a bisexual or strictly heterosexual lifestyle, thus passing on their genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side note, another historically successful strategy for homosexuals to avoid social stigma and death has been to join the (supposedly celibate) clergy. This way, they could avoid engaging in heterosexual behavior without drawing suspicion upon themselves. This perhaps explains certain observations of certain habits of certain clergies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover image by &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/@digital_e?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;digitale.de&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://unsplash.com/photos/a-close-up-of-a-structure-with-a-blue-background-2GEr4fLZt8A?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;amp;utm_source=unsplash&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>On preferred pronouns</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/p/on-preferred-pronouns/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 11:50:37 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/p/on-preferred-pronouns/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/on-preferred-pronouns/images/pexels-bertellifotografia-3856027.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;5365&#34;
	height=&#34;3577&#34;
	srcset=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/on-preferred-pronouns/images/pexels-bertellifotografia-3856027_hu_4bf6238b7ba03382.jpg 480w, //localhost:1313/p/on-preferred-pronouns/images/pexels-bertellifotografia-3856027_hu_47710a90be5a784c.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;149&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;359px&#34;
	
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is becoming customary in western societies to ask people in various settings to state their preferred pronouns. It started among younger people of the particularly woke persuasion, and it is spreading everywhere. When I find myself in such a setting, I do of course go along, because doing otherwise would be awkward, but I hope that it is only a fad which will eventually go away. While waiting to see how it pans out, let me describe a few issues I have with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Useful pre-reading: &lt;a 
   href=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/about-these-papers/&#34;
   &gt;About these papers&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by giving an example. Suppose there is a small event going on; say, a digital photography workshop. The organizer might begin by asking participants to take turns stating their names and their preferred pronouns. So, one participant says that their name is Jane and their preferred pronouns are &lt;em&gt;she&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt;, the next participant says that their name is Peter and their preferred pronouns are &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;him&lt;/em&gt;, and so on. As
the introductory round progresses, if a participant happens to state their name but omit stating their preferred pronouns, the organizer is likely to
remind them to do so, at which point they pretty much have to, otherwise it would be awkward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is being done in order to accommodate intersex persons, whose appearance and/or name might not match the pronouns that they would rather be addressed with. From what I surmise, it not only enables intersex persons to be addressed with their preferred pronouns, but it also avoids singling them out as the only ones with special pronouns, by requiring &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; to state their preferred pronouns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the issues I have with this practice. This is not a subject on which I know much, so my opinion might change as I learn more, but this is my opinion as it stands today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-above-and-beyond&#34;&gt;1. &amp;ldquo;Above and beyond&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accommodating someone without getting out of your way is one thing, and going out of your way in order to accommodate them is another thing. The process of stating not only names but also preferred pronouns requires me to state my preferred pronouns, which is something that I normally would not do; it also consumes more time overall, which is time that I normally would not spend. Thus, I think it is asking of me a level of courtesy which is above and beyond the baseline that I believe I owe to all my fellow human beings regardless of whether they are sexually conformant or divergent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-gotcha&#34;&gt;2. &amp;ldquo;Gotcha!&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Addressing someone with pronouns that differ from the pronouns I would guess based on their appearance represents a complication in my life that I could really do without. I already have a hard time remembering people&amp;rsquo;s names; having to also remember the pronouns that go with each face is really asking for a lot from me. This, in turn, makes me feel inadequate, and weary of the risk of embarrassment. This is how we make sexually divergent folks feel more included while making other groups feel more excluded. Those who are likely to feel excluded are all those who are not very deeply into wokeism, all those who suffer from Attention Deficit Disorder, (even if they are woke,) and anyone who is simply older, for reasons similar to those of ADD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-pledge-of-allegiance&#34;&gt;3. &amp;ldquo;Pledge of Allegiance&amp;rdquo;
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being asked to state my preferred pronouns, (and therefore being pretty much obliged to do so, in order to avoid friction and maintain civility,) is like requiring me to pledge my allegiance to the non-heteronormative cause. So, maybe I am allegiant to that cause, and maybe I am not; (spoiler: I am;) but challenging me to pledge my allegiance to a certain cause in front of an audience is something that does not go down very well with me; it is like asking me &amp;ldquo;are you with us, or against us?&amp;rdquo; This is a &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;divisive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;escalatory&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; tactic, which has been used on various occasions throughout history, and it was never nice. (&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_are_either_with_us,_or_against_us&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;See Wikipedia: You are either with us, or against us&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the bottom line seems to be that the wokes view the world as consisting of only two groups: them, versus the bigots. In doing so, they are completely disregarding the vast majority of people out there, who are neither woke nor bigots; this includes a huge number of people who are anywhere from neutral to positively predisposed but not as deeply concerned because they have other concerns that take priority. Thus, by creating polarization, the wokes are alienating the majority and making themselves the subject of resentment and ridicule. This is not a recipe for success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover image by
&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://www.pexels.com/photo/group-of-multiethnic-people-gathering-around-female-speaker-in-studio-3856027/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Matheus Bertelli from pexels.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Old comments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anonymous 2024-08-23 12:43:52 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree, especially your last point&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Continuous Code Quality Improvement</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/p/continuous-code-quality-improvement/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 10:48:53 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/p/continuous-code-quality-improvement/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/continuous-code-quality-improvement/images/quality.svg&#34;
	
	
	
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
&gt;

While working on code in the context of a certain task, a programmer often discovers some preexisting quality issue. When this happens, there is a choice to be made:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix the quality issue on the spot, and commit the fix in the context of the task at hand; or:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only make changes that are strictly necessary for the task at hand, and introduce a separate task for fixing the quality issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Useful pre-reading: &lt;a 
   href=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/about-these-papers/&#34;
   &gt;About these papers&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice of continuously improving the quality of the code-base is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boy-Scouting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. The term comes from a rule of the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boy Scouts of America&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; that says: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always leave the campground cleaner than you found it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. In the first chapter of &lt;em&gt;Clean Code&lt;/em&gt; by Robert C. Martin there is a
short section titled &lt;em&gt;The Boy Scout Rule&lt;/em&gt; where the author gives an adaptation of that rule for software: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always leave the code you are editing a little better than you found it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opinions vary as to exactly what constitutes Boy-Scouting, and whether it is a good thing or a bad thing. Some people believe that Boy-Scouting should be avoided; they say that when a quality issue is discovered while working on a certain task, a new ticket must always be created and handled separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I once worked at a company where different development teams within the same department had different approaches: most frowned upon boy-scouting, but some embraced it. Since Boy-Scouting had a bad name overall within that company, one team that insisted on practicing it decided to rebrand it by inventing their own term for it: they called it &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality Osmosis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. (TopDesk, Team Octarine 2016-2017.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The problem
&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arguments raised against Boy-Scouting include the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boy-Scouting interferes with time tracking, because the hours it takes to complete a certain task get inflated by fixing quality issues, whereas the hours spent on fixing quality issues is unaccounted for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boy-Scouting renders quality improvements untraceable, because each quality improvement is hidden inside a commit for some other task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boy-Scouting adds extra burden to code review, because the reviewer has to examine not only the changes for the task at hand, but also additional changes that are unrelated to, or strictly speaking unnecessary for, or in any case not directly aiming to solve, the task at hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Boy-Scouting is viewed as undesirable in some management-heavy environments because it is seen as giving programmers too much autonomy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boy-Scouting implies that programmers are free to get sidetracked, instead of always being laser-focused on (what management perceives to be) their job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boy-Scouting implies that programmers have carte blanche to be making any modifications they see fit to the code base without prior authorization, so who knows what else they might be doing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note that these concerns are rarely voiced, but often implied.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us look at the different kinds of quality issues that may be encountered while working on a task:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low-impact&lt;/strong&gt; - e.g. a misspelled identifier or a violation of formatting guidelines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medium-impact&lt;/strong&gt; - e.g. a code construct which is more convoluted than necessary and could be simplified to make it more understandable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High-impact:&lt;/strong&gt; - e.g. a previously undiscovered bug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low-impact issues&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A low impact quality issue is by definition so trivial that it is not worth creating a new task for it; imagine a ticket with the title &amp;ldquo;fix spelling mistake in identifier such-and-such&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;abstract class so-and-so constructor is public, make it protected&amp;rdquo;; nobody wants to go through the motions of creating, grooming, and resolving such tickets; everyone is better off if no such tickets ever exist. So, unless the low-impact issue gets fixed the moment it is discovered, and committed as part of the task at hand, it will never get fixed. This means that we can safely establish the following rule:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a low-impact quality issue is discovered while working on a certain task, the quality issue should be fixed on the spot, and committed as part of the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that fixing a spelling mistake may involve modifying a large number of source files, which would not otherwise need to be modified in the context of the task at hand; this means that the code reviewer will have more work to do; we will address this problem later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medium-impact and high-impact issues&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A medium-impact or high-impact quality issue does, in principle, deserve creating a separate ticket for, but first we need to ask whether it can actually be handled separately from the task at hand, because if not, then creating a separate ticket is moot point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it is known beyond a shadow of a doubt that the quality issue does not interfere at all with the task at hand, then the straightforward approach is in fact to create a separate ticket for the quality issue, and handle it after the task at hand has been completed; however, it is often very difficult to know for sure that a piece of code really does not affect another piece of code. There may be obscure mechanisms at play, through which a malfunction creeps through the system in non-obvious ways, and manifests in another place that nobody expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we come across a code construct which is convoluted or buggy, what we essentially have in our hands is code that works in mysterious ways, so we do not necessarily know exactly how it behaves; we could try to reason about that code, throw the debugger at it if necessary, get down to the bottom of it, and determine whether it does in fact interfere or not with the task at hand, but:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody has time for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is futile, because the convoluted or buggy code has to be fixed anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whatever conclusion you arrive to, can you actually be sure?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ascertaining that two different parts of a software system are completely isolated from each other is difficult, in the same way that it is difficult to ascertain pretty much anything when it comes to code. (See &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halting_problem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Halting Problem&lt;/a&gt;.) As a matter of fact, it is so difficult, that we usually prefer to not have to ascertain things ourselves, and to write tests instead, that will ascertain things for us. However, writing tests to check whether flawed code interferes or not with other code is an exercise in futility, especially if we consider that the flawed code has to be fixed, sooner or later, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, when a quality issue is discovered while working on a certain task, and we suspect that it might be interfering with the task, it must be treated as if it does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bureaucracy&#34;&gt;The bureaucracy
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, some will insist that even if the quality issue interferes, or is suspected to interfere, with the task at hand, and must therefore be resolved before the task can be completed, the quality issue must nonetheless be resolved as a separate ticket. Let us look at the workflow necessary for that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on the task at hand must be suspended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new ticket must be created for the quality issue, and given immediate priority.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new branch must be created, from master, for fixing the quality issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fix for the quality issue must be devised, coded, tested, and committed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The changes made in the new branch must undergo code review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The reviewed branch must be merged into the master branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The master branch must be merged into the branch of the task at hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merge conflicts must be resolved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on the task at hand can now resume.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that merge conflicts are very likely to happen even if nobody else in the entire shop has touched the code in the mean time, because the quality issue was discovered while working on the task at hand, therefore the code affected by fixing the quality issue most likely overlaps with code that has already been modified in the context of the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note that the programmer who is likely to fix the quality issue is the same programmer who was working on the original task, because they are probably free, since work on the original task has been suspended. When this programmer started working on the original task, they branched off from master; the code coming from master had a certain shape, and then they started making changes to it, giving it a new shape, which they are now intimately familiar with. By going back and branching off from master again in order to fix the quality issue, this programmer is now faced with the code in its original shape, which is in conflict with the shape that they have become intimately familiar with; this is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;brainfuck&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. When the programmer is done fixing the quality issue and returns to the branch of the task at hand, there is bound to be &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;more brainfuck&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, there are no limits to the bureaucracy and the inconvenience that some people are willing to suffer in the name of some purist notion of &amp;ldquo;doing things right&amp;rdquo;. I prefer a more pragmatic approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-continuous-code-quality-improvement-ccqi&#34;&gt;Enter Continuous Code Quality Improvement (CCQI)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;a.k.a. Boy-Scouting / Quality Osmosis.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a quality issue is discovered while working on a certain task, and the issue interferes, or it is suspected to interfere, with the task at hand, then the quality issue should be fixed on the spot, (while the programmer is &lt;em&gt;in the flow&lt;/em&gt;,) and committed as part of the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone wants to create a ticket, fine, but then a single commit will constitute a fix for multiple tickets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, an exception to this rule is the case where fixing the quality issue is going to be a month-long project in and of itself, in which case another pragmatic approach is necessary: make do with the quality issue as it is for the time being, and handle it later, when a month is available to spare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-about-time-tracking&#34;&gt;What about time-tracking?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, Boy-Scouting interferes with time tracking, because the hours it takes to complete a certain task get inflated by fixing quality issues, whereas the hours spent on fixing quality issues is unaccounted for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to this is simple: whoever is in charge of time-tracking should be using larger error bars. The work of the programmers is difficult enough as it stands, it will not be made more difficult for the convenience of those who do time-tracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-about-the-commit-history&#34;&gt;What about the commit history?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, Boy-Scouting renders the history of quality improvements
untraceable, because each quality improvement is hidden inside a commit for
some other task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to this is also simple: there shall be no traceable history for quality improvements, because quality improvements are being continuously applied to the code-base as it is being worked on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-about-code-review&#34;&gt;What about code review?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, Boy-Scouting adds extra burden to code review, because the reviewer has to examine not only changes pertinent to the task at hand, but also changes that are unrelated to, or strictly speaking unnecessary for, or in any case not directly aiming to solve, the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to this is the simplest of all: the reviewer needs to get used to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-what-about-the-management&#34;&gt;And what about the management?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, management tends to be skeptical of Boy-Scouting because it gives programmers too much autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to this is very similar to the solution for code review: the management needs to get used to it. If programmers are competent enough to work on software development tasks, they are competent enough to decide exactly what needs to be done in the context of each task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover image by &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://michael.gr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;michael.gr&lt;/a&gt; based on &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://thenounproject.com/icon/quality-6554761/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;&amp;ldquo;Quality&amp;rdquo; by Sutriman&lt;/a&gt; (CC BY 3.0), &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://thenounproject.com/icon/thumb-up-2107329/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;&amp;ldquo;Thumb up&amp;rdquo; by Sewon Park&lt;/a&gt; (CC BY 3.0), and &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://thenounproject.com/icon/five-stars-5786731/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;&amp;ldquo;Five Stars&amp;rdquo; by Tyler Gobberdiel&lt;/a&gt; (CC BY 3.0), from &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://thenounproject.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;the Noun Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>On the evolutionary origin of reasoning</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/p/on-the-evolutionary-origin-of-reasoning/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 11:24:24 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/p/on-the-evolutionary-origin-of-reasoning/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/on-the-evolutionary-origin-of-reasoning/images/caveman-thinking-1.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;1080&#34;
	height=&#34;1080&#34;
	srcset=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/on-the-evolutionary-origin-of-reasoning/images/caveman-thinking-1_hu_a680d3065694d80.jpg 480w, //localhost:1313/p/on-the-evolutionary-origin-of-reasoning/images/caveman-thinking-1_hu_b7767b2efb905834.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;100&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;240px&#34;
	
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biological anthropologists generally agree that humans evolved reasoning to facilitate hunting together as a group; however, there are many other species that hunt in packs, and yet reasoning is unique to humans. Therefore, in order to explain reasoning, it is not enough to consider how it was beneficial to us; we also need to consider what enabled reasoning to emerge specifically in humans as opposed to any other species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a hypothesis which attempts to explain how this happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Useful pre-reading: &lt;a 
   href=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/about-these-papers/&#34;
   &gt;About these papers&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;exaptation-of-neural-circuitry-for-arboreal-navigation&#34;&gt;Exaptation of Neural Circuitry for Arboreal Navigation
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;A hypothesis for the emergence of reasoning in early humans&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When our &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simian&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;simian&lt;/a&gt; ancestors first stepped down from the canopy of the forest to the ground of the savanna, they were still pretty well adapted to arboreal life, so they still had with them all the machinery necessary for &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arboreal_locomotion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;arboreal locomotion&lt;/a&gt; by means of &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brachiation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;brachiation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of that machinery was evident in their anatomy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stereopsis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Stereoscopic vision&lt;/a&gt; for determining distances to branches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thumb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Opposable thumbs&lt;/a&gt; for grabbing and holding on to branches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper_limb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Strong upper limbs&lt;/a&gt; for suspending the entire body weight from a branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The machinery also included a very important element in the brain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neural_circuit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;Neural circuits&lt;/a&gt; dedicated to the planning and execution of arboreal navigation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as brachiation is a formidable feat of the simian anatomy, so is arboreal navigation a formidable feat of the simian brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting from branch A to branch Z in the forest canopy involves examination of multiple alternative routes, each consisting of several successive leaps from branch to branch, where at each branch multiple choices are open, but some choices lead to dead-ends. Leaps often have to be evaluated in advance (planning) not only in order to determine the feasibility of the route as a whole, but also to find the most optimal route. The process involves some techniques which we have only started to grasp in the era of information processing, through the study of &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pathfinding&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;pathfinding&lt;/a&gt; algorithms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back-tracking: when the next leap in the path is deemed as not feasible, an alternative route can be sought from an earlier branch in the same path instead of starting from the beginning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information reuse: when it has been determined that from a certain branch X there is a path to reach branch Y, this information can be reused when an alternative way is found for arriving at branch X.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reverse pathfinding: to plan a path from branch A to branch Z one can start from A, consider leaps to branches near A, and so on; however, if most of those seem to lead to dead ends, one may alternatively plan a path by doing the reverse: starting from Z, considering feasible leaps to Z from branches near Z, and so on, until a branch is found which is known to be reachable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brachiation is an activity that simians carry out effortlessly, at incredibly high speeds, and flawlessly, because a single mistake can easily result in a
broken bone, which equates to certain death in the wild. Furthermore, (and I do not know this for sure, but I think it is a pretty safe guess,) simian
babies do not have to learn how to brachiate, they are pretty much born with the ability. Therefore, the simian brain must have built-in neural circuits specifically dedicated to the task of arboreal navigation and the planning thereof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once our simian ancestors settled on the ground of the savanna, the neural circuits for arboreal navigation fell into disuse, essentially becoming &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vestigiality&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;vestigial&lt;/a&gt;. At the same time, new challenges and opportunities arose: food on the savanna was scarce, so humans had to hunt. The hunt was generally big, and humans did not have claws and teeth, so they had to coordinate in order to be successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hypothesis is that via mechanisms that I cannot claim to know, (since I am not a bioanthropologist, nor a neurobiologist,) the neural circuitry for arboreal navigation was repurposed in the human brain for the task of reasoning. Repurposing of traits is known by evolutionary biology to be common, not only in anatomy but also in behavior; it is called &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exaptation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;exaptation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anatomical machinery that enabled simians to brachiate is still present in us today, so it is not a stretch to imagine that the neural machinery is also present. Human babies have a lot to learn until they can function autonomously in the world, but reasoning comes rather naturally to them, and education seems to build upon a preexisting foundation which innately supports reasoning. Therefore, reasoning seems to also be largely based on dedicated neural circuitry in the human brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental workflows of reasoning and arboreal navigation bear a striking resemblance to each other: from a certain set of premises, a number of potential inferences can be examined; some of those can be ignored due to being irrelevant to the desired conclusion; they correspond to leaps in directions away from the desired destination. Other potential inferences can be disregarded due to being false; these correspond to leaps that are impossible to make. Each of the remaining inferences represents a new set of premises, from which further potential inferences can be examined, thus bringing us closer and closer to the desired conclusion. Some chains of inferences lead to dead-ends, at which point we go back one or more steps to examine a different path; these correspond to back-tracking in path-finding. In all these cases, the neural circuitry we use for reasoning may be that very same neural circuitry that we used to use for arboreal navigation but fell into disuse when we came down from the trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The necessity to coordinate for hunting may have acted as a catalyst for the repurposing of neural circuitry from the task of arboreal navigation to the task of reasoning. The Gorilla is another great ape that descended from the trees to the ground, but they have remained vegetarian, so their food was free for the grabbing in the trees, and continued to be free for the grabbing on the ground. Therefore, Gorillas had no need to form packs and go hunting for food, and thus no evolutionary pressure to do any repurposing of neural circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More light might be shed on this hypothesis from research on the anatomical connectivity between the &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cerebellum&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;cerebellum&lt;/a&gt;, which is associated with motor control, and the &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frontal_lobe&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;frontal lobe&lt;/a&gt;, which is associated with problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover image: &amp;ldquo;Thinking Caveman&amp;rdquo;, AI-generated at &lt;a class=&#34;external&#34; 
   href=&#34;https://canva.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;
   &gt;canva.com&lt;/a&gt; from a prompt by michael.gr&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Trees of Eternity</title>
        <link>//localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 15:55:13 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>//localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/images/trees-of-eternity-hour-of-the-nightingale.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;2048&#34;
	height=&#34;2048&#34;
	srcset=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/images/trees-of-eternity-hour-of-the-nightingale_hu_9afa5732579d23ae.jpg 480w, //localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/images/trees-of-eternity-hour-of-the-nightingale_hu_54bd9eb33d6748dc.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;100&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;240px&#34;
	
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This band has been haunting me for the past days. I feel compelled to write about it. This post will be completely different from the kind of posts you normally see on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While going through some random playlist on YouTube I stumbled upon this band that I immediately took a liking to, which is something that does not happen often. When I tried to find out a bit more information about them, what I discovered wrecked me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name of the band is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trees of Eternity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and they are said to belong to the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Doom/Gothic Metal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; genre, which is not exactly the kind of music that I listen to, but in the case of this particular band, their sound matches my taste very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was intending to listen to them while working on my computer, but there was something about their sound that grabbed hold of me and I could not help but switch to watch the videos of their songs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of their official videos feature their singer, a beautiful lady in her thirties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/images/aleah-stanbridge.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;750&#34;
	height=&#34;750&#34;
	srcset=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/images/aleah-stanbridge_hu_1d1054a012fe5955.jpg 480w, //localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/images/aleah-stanbridge_hu_64226c580a5887f3.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;100&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;240px&#34;
	
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She has an extraordinarily soft, breathy voice the like of which I have never heard before. It has been described as delicate, angelic, ethereal. It is feminine, but not girly; I would actually call it solemn. Because she sings so softly, she keeps her mouth very close to the microphone, so you can hear her inhaling between sentences, and this creates a feeling of presence, as if she is singing right next to you. Their instruments sound like &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symphonic/Goth Metal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, but without excitement or fanfare; they play masterfully, but they stay in the background so as to keep her beautiful voice verily in the foreground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The grand sum of all this is definitely grave and gloomy, but mature, and completely free from pretentiousness and hyperbole, which are so common in the genre. It constitutes the most cohesive sound I have heard in many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the videos, the background is nature; a Nordic forest; barren tree branches in darkness; gray sea waves crashing on shore; empty fields of tall grass with a somewhat withered look. In both videos she is wearing the same black sun necklace. In one video (&lt;em&gt;Sinking Ships&lt;/em&gt;) she appears with flowing long black hair; in the other, (&lt;em&gt;Broken Mirror&lt;/em&gt;) her head is covered in a veil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so good. The trouble started during a scene in the &lt;em&gt;Broken Mirrors&lt;/em&gt; video where the wind momentarily lifts the veil from her face and  she looks at the viewer with a distinctly eerie gaze that I found somewhat unsettling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/images/trees-of-eternity-broken-mirror.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;1200&#34;
	height=&#34;630&#34;
	srcset=&#34;//localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/images/trees-of-eternity-broken-mirror_hu_e5906567da4ebc53.jpg 480w, //localhost:1313/p/trees-of-eternity/images/trees-of-eternity-broken-mirror_hu_4af28bea941d7a3a.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;190&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;457px&#34;
	
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, I was tempted to dismiss it as just another goth acting before the camera as is befitting to a goth, but as the scene faded into the next, I was left with the impression that her gaze had been completely free from the overstatement which is characteristic of pretense; there was something inexplicably genuine about it, but I could not tell what it was. Since I was not sure what was going on, I could not assign much weight to it at that moment, but in retrospect, I would say that it was the kind of gaze that would make the blood freeze in your veins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking to dissolve the mystery, my eyes fell upon the comments below the video. I read the first one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commenter had written that they were extremely sad, because they had just discovered this band, (like me,) and they were completely blown away by the beauty of their sound, (like me,) and they had been hoping to hear more from them in the future, (like me,) but they had just found out that the singer had died.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to look them up on Wikipedia, in part because I like fact-checking things, in part because I wished this to turn out to be false, and in part out of curiosity: common causes of death for rock singers are drugs, alcohol, suicide, or combinations thereof; so, what was it going to be for that angelic voice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Wikipedia begins by stating that Trees of Eternity &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;was&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; a musical collaboration between certain individuals which ended with the death of their singer, Aleah Stanbridge, in 2016. It goes on to mention that the band members and guest contributors were all acclaimed musicians, having previously played with well-known bands such as &lt;em&gt;Katatonia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wintersun&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Paradise Lost&lt;/em&gt;, which even I have heard of, despite them belonging to a genre that I don&amp;rsquo;t normally listen to; their drummer had even played on occasion with &lt;em&gt;Nightwish&lt;/em&gt;, which used to be one of my favorite bands. This explained the masterfulness of the instrumentation. I kept reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, Aleah Stanbridge died at the age of 39, from cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fact, along with her unsettling gaze in the video, made me curious, so I looked for information about the timeline of the band.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They formed in 2013. They mostly worked remotely, so progress must have been slow. At the time of her death in April of 2016 the band had not released anything yet. Their one and only record, &lt;em&gt;The Hour Of The Nightingale&lt;/em&gt; was released half a year later, in November of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, cancer is not something that kills you one night in your sleep while nobody expected it; it takes time. This is perhaps the greatest tragedy with this disease: you know well in advance. So, I thought that this timeline was a bit odd. That is when I begun to suspect the nature of the musical collaboration that I had stumbled upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back to the track list looking for clues to support my hypothesis, and sure enough, the title of the very first song served as an immediate confirmation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;01. My Requiem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lyrics are also in line with that, in this and most other songs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was when I realized just what it was about the lady&amp;rsquo;s gaze in the &lt;em&gt;Broken Mirror&lt;/em&gt; video that made it so unsettling: this woman standing before the camera was not acting; she was dying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was when I realized that the &lt;em&gt;Sinking Ships&lt;/em&gt; video, showing her with long flowing hair, must have been shot early on, while the &lt;em&gt;Broken Mirror&lt;/em&gt; video, where her head was covered in a veil, must have been from later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was when I realized that in the &lt;em&gt;Broken Mirror&lt;/em&gt; video she appears standing, or walking, but she is not actually singing; maybe she had no voice anymore at that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was when I started experiencing in full the gut-wrenching effect of many of the verses, like &lt;em&gt;my season has come to an end&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;embrace this as a Nightingale in song&lt;/em&gt;, or perhaps the most gut-wrenching of all: &lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;of a fate worse than death, condemned to silence.&lt;/em&gt; There are many other verses that have an immensely powerful meaning in light of the circumstances, I will leave them for you do discover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this has been publicized; you have no way of suspecting anything unless you pay attention to hints, and no way of knowing unless you connect the dots. If you do not know, they are just your usual morbid gothic lyrics; but if you know, they are heart-felt devastation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was also when I realized how truly superb the instrumentation and the mastering had been. These were all such accomplished musicians that in the associated literature someone at some point described them as a &lt;em&gt;super-group&lt;/em&gt;. Whatever; the thing is, accomplishment builds egos, and with ego usually comes an extravagant style of playing, a prime example of which is, say, Joe Satriani. Yet, these musicians produced music of excellent quality while keeping their tone down so as to keep that lady&amp;rsquo;s ethereal voice always at the front: in the entire record there is not a single guitar solo; not a single attention-catching shred; not a single roaring drum roll; at the same time, there is absolutely nothing inadequate about it: from start to finish, the music is rich, sophisticated heavy metal, mostly in ballad style, at times in epic style, but always serving as a bed for her voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music is precisely what it had to be for the occasion: masterful, but intentionally understated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the record was not about them; it was about her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How often does it happen that after receiving a medical death sentence someone will continue to make music instead of withdrawing and withering away? I do not know, but I would be willing to guess that it must be exceedingly rare. I used to suspect that Roy Orbinson&amp;rsquo;s comeback at the end of the eighties with the re-make of &lt;em&gt;Pretty Woman&lt;/em&gt; and with new hits like &lt;em&gt;The End of the Line&lt;/em&gt; was such a case, because he died very soon afterwards, but as it turns out he died from heart attack, so that was probably not it. But even if someone received the bad news and decided to keep on keeping on, how likely would it be that they would be singing about death? And how likely would it be that they would be singing about their own death?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may well be that Trees of Eternity is a project unprecedented in the history of music-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, before us lies an interesting phenomenon: we have the entire doom/gothic genre of music, a huge death cult obsessed with all things morbid, but actually full of pretentiousness, hyperbole, and copious amounts of black make-up; and sitting right at the fringe of this genre we have this one little gem of a record, which contains in it more death than the entire genre combined. Is it not ironic?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These realizations appear to be completely lost on critics who have reviewed &lt;em&gt;The Hour Of The Nightingale&lt;/em&gt;. They begin by acknowledging that it is tragic that the singer has died, and then they proceed to evaluate the record as they would evaluate any other record. At best, they find it very good music, but the circumstances under which the record was made seem to escape them, so they fail to appreciate that it does in fact sound precisely as it ought to sound, let alone that &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;no one alive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is entitled to find fault with it. One critic complains that most songs are in ballad style while he would have preferred more variation; whatever; another complains that overall, the record strays too much in the direction of pop, whereas I suppose he would have wanted it to sound more gothic; whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the thing: in the face of actual death, the entire gothic genre suddenly begins to look like a highly inappropriate funny little circus. Death in itself is morbid enough; no need for black lipstick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artist: &lt;strong&gt;Trees of Eternity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Album: &lt;strong&gt;The Hour of the Nightingale&lt;/strong&gt; (2016)&lt;br&gt;
Song: &lt;strong&gt;My Requiem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Light&lt;br&gt;
Blistering, so bright&lt;br&gt;
Realign my core&lt;br&gt;
Lenses open wide&lt;br&gt;
Coming into form&lt;br&gt;
The imprint of a life&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Chorus]&lt;br&gt;
Too late you&amp;rsquo;re calling out my name&lt;br&gt;
To raise me up out of my grave&lt;br&gt;
Alive in memory I&amp;rsquo;ll stay&lt;br&gt;
If you shun these waters where I lay&lt;br&gt;
If you shun these waters where I lay&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Night&lt;br&gt;
Curtains coming down&lt;br&gt;
Into the shade I stray&lt;br&gt;
Losing all I&amp;rsquo;ve found&lt;br&gt;
To my own dismay&lt;br&gt;
My season has come to an end&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Chorus]&lt;br&gt;
Too late you&amp;rsquo;re calling out my name&lt;br&gt;
To raise me up out of my grave&lt;br&gt;
Alive in memory I&amp;rsquo;ll stay&lt;br&gt;
If you shun these waters where I lay&lt;br&gt;
If you shun these waters where I lay&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leave me to rest&lt;br&gt;
Too drained to rise&lt;br&gt;
To try to detect&lt;br&gt;
Any light&lt;br&gt;
at the end of the tunnel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Chorus]&lt;br&gt;
Too late you&amp;rsquo;re calling out my name&lt;br&gt;
To raise me up out of my grave&lt;br&gt;
Alive in memory I&amp;rsquo;ll stay&lt;br&gt;
If you shun these waters where I lay&lt;br&gt;
If you shun these waters where I lay&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
