<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogging on Michael's Blog</title><link>https://blog.michael.gr/tags/blogging/</link><description>Recent content in Blogging on Michael's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Michael Belivanakis (a.k.a. Mike Nakis)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:41:36 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.michael.gr/tags/blogging/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>New year, new blog!</title><link>https://blog.michael.gr/post/2026-01-08-new-blog/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 12:05:54 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.michael.gr/post/2026-01-08-new-blog/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.michael.gr/post/2026-01-08-new-blog/media/new-blog.svg"
loading="lazy"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of today, I have a brand new blog. The old posts are still here, but the look and feel, and everything under the hood, is different. Everything is still free for me, except the domain name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post lists the technologies involved in editing and publishing my blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To read why I transitioned from my old blog to this new blog, see &lt;a
href="https://blog.michael.gr/post/2026-01-07-goodbye-blogger/"
&gt;Goodbye blogger!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="repository-github"&gt;Repository: GitHub
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="drop-cap-image" src="media/logo-github.svg" alt="GitHub logo"/&gt;The blog content now consists of markdown files and image files. They all live in a private repository on &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GitHub" target="_blank"
&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, a clone of which I have on my local computer. Every once in a while I push to origin, essentially creating a backup. This means that I can always view the history of all changes I make to my blog. Also, if something bad happens to my local computer, I have everything on GitHub. If something bad happens to GitHub, I have everything on my local computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="markdown-editor-obsidian"&gt;Markdown editor: Obsidian
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="drop-cap-image" src="media/logo-obsidian.svg" alt="Obsidian logo"/&gt;For editing the markdown files I use &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obsidian_%28software%29" target="_blank"
&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt;, a cross-platform desktop application which is proprietary but free. Obsidian gives me a very nice markdown editor, which, although not perfect, is probably the best in existence. Most importantly, Obsidian keeps all my links in sync, so I can freely rename content files and move them around without fearing that the links might be broken. Obsidian even has git integration, so I can push my files to GitHub with a click of a button. The important thing is that my blog content is now in an open format, as opposed to Blogger format, or WordPress format, etc. this means that I could switch to another markdown editor if I wanted to, without having to change the slightest thing in my blog content to accommodate that editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="site-builder-hugo"&gt;Site builder: Hugo
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="drop-cap-image" src="media/logo-hugo.svg" alt="Hugo logo"/&gt;For converting the markdown files into HTML I use &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugo_%28software%29" target="_blank"
&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, a free, open-source, cross-platform, command-line tool that is distinguished for being much faster than other tools that serve the same purpose. Hugo reads the entire directory containing my markdown files, plus another entire directory containing a &amp;quot;Hugo theme&amp;quot;, and produces a new directory containing a static website. Hugo then remains running, acting as a local web-server, making my website available on http://localhost, so that I can view it using my web-browser. As an added bonus, each time I modify any of the content files or theme files, Hugo causes the browser to immediately show the change. Hugo can be replaced with something else, at the cost of learning a new theming mechanism and redoing theme customization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="hugo-theme-stack"&gt;Hugo theme: 'Stack'
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="drop-cap-image" src="media/logo-stack.svg" alt="Stack Hugo theme logo"/&gt;The theme that I currently use is based on the free, open-source &lt;a class="external"
href="https://github.com/CaiJimmy/hugo-theme-stack" target="_blank"
&gt;&amp;quot;Stack&amp;quot; theme for Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. I have customized the original theme to suit my needs, and my custom files also live on GitHub, alongside the content files. (Same repository but different directory.) When the original theme gets updated by its author, I use a git merge tool to combine the new changes with mine, resolving conflicts if necessary, just as I would do if I was merging program code. This theme could, in principle, be replaced with another, but that would require redoing the customization work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="commenting-intensedebate"&gt;Commenting: IntenseDebate
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="drop-cap-image" src="media/logo-intensedebate.svg" alt="IntenseDebate logo"/&gt;For commenting I use &lt;a class="external"
href="https://intensedebate.com/" target="_blank"
&gt;IntenseDebate&lt;/a&gt;, which is a free service provided by &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automattic" target="_blank"
&gt;Automattic&lt;/a&gt; (sic), the makers of &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WordPress" target="_blank"
&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravatar" target="_blank"
&gt;Gravatar&lt;/a&gt;. They provide a small HTML snippet which I have added at the right place in my theme, so it shows at the bottom of every post. The snippet handles everything comment-related: showing existing comments, adding a new comment, subscribing for notifications, etc. Blog commenting is all about spam control, which is a fairly complicated topic, and Automattic (sic) have a lot of experience with spam control, so I trust that they do it right. If it turns out that IntenseDebate does not suit my needs, I can easily replace it with something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="hosting-netlify"&gt;Hosting: Netlify
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="drop-cap-image" src="media/logo-netlify.svg" alt="Netlify logo"/&gt;For serving my static web-site to the world, I currently use a free hosting plan with &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netlify" target="_blank"
&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt;, a well known web hosting company headquartered in San Francisco, USA. This free plan seems to offer enough to suit my needs, and can certainly be upgraded in the future if my personal blog grows into a blogging empire or something. Once the static website has been generated by Hugo, and I decide that it is ready for publishing, I push it to yet another private GitHub repository, and from there Netlify automatically clones it, processes it, and makes it available to the world. If it turns out that Netlify does not suit my needs, I can move my blog elsewhere. (I am planning to give CloudFlare a try.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="vector-image-editor-inkscape"&gt;Vector image editor: Inkscape
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="drop-cap-image" src="media/logo-inkscape.svg" alt="Inkscape logo"/&gt;Finally, since I am now in full possession and full control of my own content, I have replaced many of the PNG and JPG images in my blog with SVG images. For that, I use &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inkscape" target="_blank"
&gt;Inkscape&lt;/a&gt;, a free and open-source SVG editor. I like SVG so much that on some occasions I have gone through the trouble using the tracing feature of Inkscape to produce SVG images from raster images. (This requires editing afterwards, so it is time consuming.) Again, the SVG format is open, so I can switch from Inkscape to any alternative without having to change the slightest thing in my content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is not to say that all of the above tools and technologies are without problems; I will probably be writing some grumpy post in the future listing the issues that I have with each of them. But for now, I am really enjoying the new look of my blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover image: the logos of the technologies that I am currently using for blogging.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Goodbye blogger!</title><link>https://blog.michael.gr/post/2026-01-07-goodbye-blogger/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 08:33:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://blog.michael.gr/post/2026-01-07-goodbye-blogger/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://blog.michael.gr/post/2026-01-07-goodbye-blogger/media/blogger-logo.svg"
loading="lazy"
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first attempt at blogging started in 2001, with a web-site entirely hand-made in HTML. It was crude, it had no commenting, and it was very difficult to maintain it, so it was necessarily tiny. Back then, finding a web host that was both free and would allow you to use your own domain name for free was quite difficult, so I had no option but to go with various questionable free hosting places. First it was &lt;strong&gt;united.net.kg&lt;/strong&gt;. (Where &lt;strong&gt;kg&lt;/strong&gt; is the top-level-domain of &lt;a class="external"
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyrgyzstan" target="_blank"
&gt;Kyrgyzstan&lt;/a&gt;.) Predictably, it one day just disappeared. Then, it was &lt;strong&gt;digitalrice.com&lt;/strong&gt;. It had the same fate. Starting from 2007 and lasting until yesterday, I had been hosting my blog on &lt;a class="external"
href="https://blogger.com" target="_blank"
&gt;blogger.com&lt;/a&gt; (formerly blogspot.com) which, luckily, has been stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blogger had several advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being backed by google, it was unlikely to disappear suddenly and without a warning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It would make use of my own domain-name for free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It made posting, editing, creating drafts, etc. reasonably easy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It provided a rudimentary commenting facility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It had a built-in search facility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It used a responsive theme so my blog looked decent on mobile too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It needed very little setup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was reasonably customizable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It even allowed editing the actual HTML body of each post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the ability to use my own domain name for free is why I chose Blogger over WordPress, which checks all the same boxes and more, but wants to charge me a few dollars per year to provide me with the luxury of having my own domain name point to my own blog. I get it that they somehow need to make money, I am not complaining, it is just that if I can have something for free, I would rather have it for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, blogger has a number of shortcomings which have been bugging me for years:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The looks of my blog were kind of dated even right from the start, and that was almost twenty years ago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The (supposedly, but not really) WYSIWYG editor would foul up the HTML as part of its normal operation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The post editing page wasted an awful lot of screen real estate, providing a very small scrollable viewport for editing the post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certain blog management tasks were very difficult, for example curating tags, and some were outright impossible, for example finding out which images are unused in order to delete them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only a handful of file types were supported, and this did not include ZIP files. Not supporting zip files might be kind of understandable, but still, a great limitation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The commenting facility was very crude, resulting in a very poor user experience, which in turn resulted in many people never bothering to leave a comment. One user once told me that they tried to leave a comment but it was lost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spam comments were a very frequent phenomenon, meaning that spam filters were either very poor or completely non-existent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, blogger had certain shortcomings that were outright unacceptable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It did not support images in SVG format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It did not maintain any kind of edit history of posts and drafts &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; it did not support fetching them from GitHub.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It did not support markdown.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It did absolutely nothing to maintain link integrity in posts containing links to other posts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It had been abandoned by google; they did not seem to be putting any work into it, so the shortcomings were never going to be addressed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, these shortcomings classified blogger as a platform to use only until a better alternative is found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, over the years, every once in a while I would look around for alternatives to blogger. However, I was not finding anything that did not suffer from even worse shortcomings. For example, at some point I tried medium.com, but I got very quickly annoyed by their delusional aspiration to charge people money for reading blog content, their preposterous passwordless sign-in mechanism, and their ridiculous restriction on how much content you are allowed to read before you have to sign-in, at which point you are forced to use their preposterous passwordless sign-in mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The breakthrough happened recently, when I discovered that nowadays there is a whole world out there, of people creating blogs as markdown files hosted on GitHub, which are then converted into static HTML websites using various tools, and then published on regular web hosting providers. So, I decided to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, I first had to convert my blog from blogger HTML to markdown. Blogger did in fact generate an export of my blog when I asked it to, but it was a very complicated set of data without a shred of documentation as to how to make sense out of it. I had to do some reverse engineering to figure things out, and then I had to write an application in C# which read the export, parsed the html, converted it to markdown, fixed links between posts, fixed links to media, processed and added visitor comments, etc. It was a huge amount of work. For any brave souls that might want to try their luck and follow my steps, the DotNet/C# project is here: &lt;a class="external"
href="https://github.com/mikenakis/MarkdownFromBlogger" target="_blank"
&gt;https://github.com/mikenakis/MarkdownFromBlogger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I converted my blogger content to markdown and media files, the next step was to create my new blog from those. How I created it, and how I maintain it, is described in &lt;a
href="https://blog.michael.gr/post/2026-01-08-new-blog/"
&gt;New year, new blog!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover image: the blogger logo from &lt;a class="external"
href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Blogger_logo.svg" target="_blank"
&gt;wikimedia.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>